Guide to the Aleksandr Kazem-Bek papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series V: Printed Materials, 1928-1968
  - Subseries V.1: Various printed brochures, articles, biographies, publications, periodicals, journals, etc.
    - Russie newspaper, 5 January 1939 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - The Third Hour journal, Paris 1946-1947 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Varia (Box 6, Folder 9)
      (various printed leaflets and brochures, printed journals, including National Council Outlook, February 1952
  - Subseries V.2: La Vie Intellectuelle
    - March 1947-February 1948 (Box 7)
  - Subseries V.3: Religious Journals, 1954-1968
    - Zhurnal Moskovskoi Patriarkhii 1961-1968 (Box 8)
    - One Church/Edinaia tserkov' 1954-1956 (Box 8)
- Series VI: Subject Files, 1921-1965
  - AATSEL (American Association of Teachers of Slavic and East European Languages)
    - 1945 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      (news bulletin)
    - 1946-1949 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      (news bulletins)
    - 1946-1951
      - Coleman, Arthur P. "American Area and Language Courses in Slavic and East European Studies, 1946-1947." (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - American Slavic and East European Review, vol. V, Nos. 14-15 (1946): 162-192 (Box 9, Folder 3)
        (offprint)
      - Invitations, notes, meeting minutes, contact and member information, language program drafts, letterheads, teaching methods (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Appointment to India/Pakistan (Box 9, Folder 4)
    (correspondence with dignitaries, letters of recommendation, contact information, other letters relating to travel needs and arrangements).
    (See also: related correspondence with M. Fayer in Series I: Correspondence--Correspondence with universities, 2, Folder 24
  - Berdiaev, Nikolai (Box 9, Folder 5)
    (handwritten and typed lists of written materials by Berdiaev)
  - Cameron, W.J., "Russia" speech, 25 January 1942 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    (printed copy)
  - Chekhov Publishing House, 1951-1953 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    (professional correspondence, clippings about Chekhov)
  - Connecticut College, 1946-1956 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    (professional correspondence, invitations, offers of employment, notices of appointment, etc.)
  - Connecticut College cultural events, 1946-1965 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    (brochures, programs, flyers, etc.)
  - De Gaulle, Charles (Box 9, Folder 10)
    (clippings, "Societé d'Histoire de la Revolution Francaise," New York, 1945)
  - Employment History in the US, 1940-1954 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    (correspondence, letters of recommendation, application forms, memoranda, etc.)
    See also: materials on appointment to India/Pakistan, 9, Folder 5)
  - Episcopal Church, 1948 (The Living Church, 18 July 1948 - 29 August 1948) (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Ford Foundation (Wasson, Gordon R. Toward a Russian Policy: A second look at some popular beliefs about Russia and the Soviet Union, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    (booklet inscribed by author 21 January 1952 clippings and professional correspondence)
  - General Aleksandr Spiridovich (Box 9, Folder 14)
    (black and white photograph, handwritten notes)
  - Kazem-Bek's entry of Gogol for the National Encyclopedia, 1947-1949 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    (handwritten and typed drafts, professional correspondence with Encyclopedia Department)
  - Lecture notes
    (handwritten and typed notes for essays)
    - "Chem grozila by russkomu narodu pobeda Germanii" (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - "On Modernism" (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - "Renaissance" (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Lecture notes on Block and Neosymbolists (Box 9, Folder 17)
    (untitled, handwritten)
  - Lecture notes on Dostoyevsky (Box 9, Folder 18)
    (handwritten)
  - Lecture notes on Russian literature (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - List of persons either connected with Russian culture or former Russians in the USA (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Local Assembly of Russian Orthodox Church, 1 February 1945 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Materials on the history of Russia (Box 10, Folder 4)
    (untitled and undated copied materials)
  - Memoranda and Correspondence with U.S. War Department, including DeWitt Clinton Poole, Lovering Hill, Edward G. Lansdale, Edward L. Barlow, 1940-1944 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    (also includes queries concerning employment possibilities, submission of articles, personal correspondence with U.S. War Department staff, copy of "Some Notes on Russia" by George Knupffer, etc.)
  - Mladoross movement, 1921-1938 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    (various typed and printed materials relating to the Young Russian party)
  - Mladoross movement 2, 1939-1943 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Nasha oborona, May 1942 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    (undated movie still from Aleksandr Nevsky)
  - Notes on ballet (Box 10, Folder 9)
    (handwritten notes, invitation to Olga Tarassova School of Ballet Annual Recital, 26 May 1946)
  - Novoie russkoie slovo, 1944-1945 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    (clippings and professional correspondence)
  - Publisher leaflets (Box 10, Folder 11)
    (brochures, book catalogues, etc.)
  - Russian language programs and notes (Box 10, Folder 12)
    (brochures, leaflets, and notes relating to various existing Russian language programs in the US)
  - Russian Imperial family in emigration (Box 10, Folder 13)
    (G.K. Graf, Vospominaniia o Ieia Velichestve Gosudaryne Imperatritse Viktorii Feodorovne with inscription, clippings)
  - Smirnov, N.P. (Box 10, Folder 14)
    (typed biographical notes)
  - Third Hour magazine, December 1945 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    (letter from Helen Izvolski and article by Kazem-Bek entitled "Pochin Stefana Permskogo")
  - Tolstoy, Andrew. Protest to the UN, 1949-1950 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    (typed copies of Tolstoy's protest and ensuing correspondence between Tolstoy, Patrick Home, and Byron Price)
  - Travel, 1950-1955 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    (itineraries, insurance, ticket stubs, brochures etc.)
  - Visit of Archbishop Aleksei, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    (various materials, letters, letterheads, speeches, memoranda relating to the visit of Archbishop Aleksei of the Moscow Patriarchate)
  - YMCA, 1941-1953 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    (correspondence with Paul Anderson, other materials relating to Kazem-Bek's work with the War Prisoner's Aid of the Young Men's Christian Association
- Series VII: Clippings
  - Organized in chronological order (Box 11-13)
- Series VIII: Flat Files
  - Organized in alphabetical then chronological order (Box 14-19)
  - Oversized materials (Box 14-19)
    (poster for the World Council of Churches, Kazem-Bek travel documents, La Vie Illustrée, 27 September 1901 printed biography of Aleksandr Kasimovich Kazem-Bek, grandfather of Aleksandr L'vovich Kazem-Bek, newspapers